Nil-Jana Akpinar

♠ https://nakpinar.github.io/

in linkedin.com/in/nil-jana-akpinar

☑ nakpinar@andrew.cmu.edu

9 @niljanaakpinar

PROFILE

PhD candidate in statistics and machine learning with focus on Responsible AI, advised by Alexandra Chouldechova and Zachary Lipton. My current research takes a data and algorithm-centered perspective to study the impact of noise, proxies and dynamics on fairness in machine learning.

EDUCATION

PhD in Statistics and Machine Learning (joint), Carnegie Mellon University	Aug 2018 -
MS in Statistics, Carnegie Mellon University	Aug 2018 - May 2020
MS in Mathematics, University of Freiburg (Germany)	Oct 2015 - July 2018
BS in Economics, University of Freiburg (Germany)	Oct 2013 - Sept 2017
BS in Mathematics, University of Freiburg (Germany)	Oct 2012 - Sept 2015

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- Akpinar, N.-J., Lipton, Z., Chouldechova, A. (2023) Non-universal data: The impact of unobserved feature missingness on algorithmic fairness. Under review.
- o Akpinar, N.-J.*, Leqi, L.*, Hadfield-Menell, D. and Lipton, Z. (2022) Counterfactual Metrics for Auditing Black-Box Recommender Systems for Ethical Concerns. Workshop on Responsible Decision Making in Dynamic Environments. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2022). Working paper.
- o Akpinar, N.-J., Nagireddy, M., Stapelton, L., Cheng, H.-F., Zhu, H., Wu, S. and Heidari, H. (2022) A Sandbox Tool to Bias(Stress)-Test Fairness Algorithms. Poster at the Conference on Equity and Access in Algorithms, Mechanisms, and Optimization (EAAMO 2022). Full paper under review, preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.10233.
- o Akpinar, N.-J., DiCiccio, C., Nandy, P. and Basu, K. (2022) Long-Term Dynamics of Fairness Intervention in Connection Recommender Systems. AAAI / ACM Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Ethics, and Society (AIES 2022).
- Akpinar, N.-J., De-Arteaga, M. and Chouldechova, A. (2021) The effect of differential victim crime reporting on predictive policing systems. Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (FAccT 2021).
- o Akpinar, N.-J., Ramdas, A. and Acar, U. (2020) Analyzing Student Strategies In Blended Courses Using Clickstream Data. Thirteenth International Conference on Educational Data Mining (EDM 2020).
- Akpinar, N.-J., Kratzwald, B. and Feuerriegel, S. (2020). Sample Complexity Bounds for Recurrent Neural Networks with Application to Combinatorial Graph Problems. Thirty-Fourth Conference on Artifical Intelligence (AAAI 2020) (Student Abstract).
- * denotes equal contribution

SELECTED AWARDS

- Amazon Graduate Research Fellowship (2021)
- o AAAI best three minute student presentation award (2020)
- o Full study scholarship by the German National Academic Foundation (2013 2018)

EMPLOYMENT

LinkedIn Corporation

Sunnyvale, CA

Artificial Intelligence - Machine Learning Engineering Intern

May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Research on long-term dynamics of fairness enhancement in two-sided marketplace settings.
- o Manager: Sakshi Jain (Responsible AI team)

LinkedIn Corporation

Sunnyvale, CA

Fairness and Privacy Research Engineering Intern

May 2020 - Aug 2020

- o Developed methods for data anonymization and built a Named Entity Recognition machine learning pipeline.
- Manager: Ting Chen (Anti-Abuse team)